[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers
on the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com game for more information
hello everyone this is velena for
software engineering radio
today with me on the show sean
wildermoot he has been tinkering with
computers and software since he got a
vic-20 back in the early 80s
sean has been a microsoft mvp since 2003
and is the author of over 20 pluralsight
courses and eight books
he is an international conference
speaker and he has recently released his
first feature-length film
hello world the film a documentary about
software developers today
welcome to the show sean i'm really
excited to meet you
thank you how are you doing today i'm
fine
really excited to talk about your film
because that is going to be the episode
of today's show
as i said you just released a film
called hello world which shines a light
on the history of programming and how it
became
a majority white male dominated industry
what made you want to make this movie
why is such a movie needed
well it's interesting i i didn't mean to
make this movie i sort of accidentally
made it
what i mean by that is i uh
started to make a movie that i wanted to
be sort of a love letter to the industry
and what ended up coming out of that was
that i realized that
most of the people i was interviewing
were
just just looked like me they were yeah
western
europe as well as north american they
were
white straight you know all the
different identifiers you can think of
and i realized that i hadn't noticed
that there was a lack of diversity it
wasn't just that
i knew about it and wasn't doing
anything about it but it didn't even
occur to me to
notice i'd just gotten used to it being
a boys club
that's that's so interesting that it
took you that movie to realize that
and probably my perspective being a
woman in
computing has been a bit different it
stood out to me a bit earlier in my life
i'm sure it did then the question of
course is
like why does that matter why is it
important
to shed a light on who's in computing
well i think it's been interesting that
we have a lack of diversity and we have
a lack of
understanding about different groups
when we're building software
this ends up happening a lot you know
facial recognition
typically hasn't worked well with with
uh people of color
because a lot of times there weren't
people on those teams
the people who developed air bags had
never tested them on women so early on
a lot of women were getting hurt when
they were getting in
accidents being hurt by the airbag
itself so we have a lot of ways that i
think we can improve software
development by embracing the ideas
around inclusion and diversity certainly
there's a
the right thing to do and social justice
reasons for
increasing diversity but i think we can
also focus on
the fact that when we're writing
software if we're in a bubble of what we
think is
the right thing to do we're not going to
be writing software that's as good
as if we had people from different
backgrounds yeah we actually did an
episode on that for people
interested to know more about gender and
programming design
you know in episode 380 on gender mac we
interviewed professor burnett
and she said something similar to you
that for example the idea that people
don't read the manual
that's a very male idea because female
computer users are way more likely to
actually read the manual because
they are more worried about getting it
wrong so they want to read up more
so a user interface for women users
might look really different
for male users and people as you say
just has haven't really thought about
that because
the teams are mainly male and they're
like oh you know we don't need a manual
because who's going to read it well
turns out
women are way more likely to actually
read it
and in the us it's not just the lack of
women and software
it's also the lack of minorities so
american black
uh developers and uh latinx developers
in the u.s and
canada really are way less represented
than even women are
in this in the united states black
developers make up about four and a half
percent
and latinx developers make up about five
and a half percent of the total
number of developers and that just
doesn't that doesn't make
any sense when the percentages at least
in the united states are much higher
than that
just of the general population and and
do we understand
why that is both for women and also for
black and latinx
people why don't they pursue careers in
software
well there's there's different reasons
for different groups it's not
one simple problem women were the first
software developers and so
it used to be very dominated by women in
fact the first eight uh
software developers that actually worked
on hardware were not you know talking
about
uh ada lovelace time but in the 40s in
the united states
they were all women because software was
thought of as
as sort of a um something secretaries
should do that the
the men were going to go ahead and
create the hardware and the software
wasn't that important
they didn't really they sort of didn't
think it was going to be as important as
it was
and you know even in the 1960s it was
still considered
a great career for women cosmopolitan
magazine had a great article about it
you know and so with women
it was a bit of a few things we talked
to the
president of harvey mudd college in
california and she talked about
that it used to be that if you wanted to
be in computers
if you want to work with computers you
went to college to learn how to work
with computers
and when personal computers started to
come into the homes in the 70s and the
80s and
and in the 90s they generally were
were taken over by the boys
because a lot of these computers also
had computer games
which girls were less interested in so
by time they got to college
they felt behind even if they were
trying to pursue it like
the boys had been programming and
writing little things so they understood
sort of the basis of computers before
they got there
and and it meant retention at the
at the at the college level was really
difficult
in the case of minority access it really
comes
down to levels of prosperity so the fact
is that
when i was a teenager in the 80s
i was very lucky to have a computer but
people that were
black and latinx certainly when i was a
kid
the chance of them having a computer
just because it was cost prohibitive
was really difficult and then it became
like they didn't see themselves
in that role because we've never really
modeled
black and latinx people as developers
you don't see them
very often on tv it's usually someone
that looks like me
you know the comic book guy on the
simpsons for example like that's what we
think of as
what developers look like and so it's
harder for women
and i think especially uh minorities
to see themselves in the job to see how
they would fit in
yeah so i think you're mentioning two
important points there
one is for for both groups i get yes
early access if you're a child
having a computer and being allowed to
play with it and to explore it
and the other one is role models seeing
people in the industry that look like
you
that talk like you that dress like you
to to
see oh this is something i could become
in the future
yeah it's interesting when uh uh one of
the things i i
talk about in the movie is the effect of
stereotypes like when we think of
of computer software in in movies and
tvs and those sorts of things
we get the same stereotype over and over
again and
i don't know whether you've seen
jurassic park but in jurassic park
there's a
there's a programmer that is central to
that story
and so when you ask somebody that's seen
jurassic park what
do you remember the software guy the
tech guy in that movie they go oh yeah
yeah he's the
heavyset white guy right and in that
same scene they pan over
from samuel l jackson who is the head of
i.t
in jurassic park but no one remembers
that because that doesn't fit their
stereotype
it doesn't fit what they think a
developer looks like and that that has a
as a profound influence on people's
choices and i also want to zoom into
not just people choosing themselves not
to have a software career but also the
influence of
society on that or maybe parents saying
to
girls or parenting to to their family
members oh this career isn't for you
or professors at a university um like
maybe this is a weird question but whose
fault is this is it the fault
of people not choosing a career or is it
the
fold of society pushing people out of
the careers
in the film we don't i don't have an
answer like if i could solve this i
wanted to made a film i would have
went out and solved it right it's it's
one of those situations where
uh there isn't a simple answer some of
it is the
age-old women are told they aren't good
at
math and science and so we've had
trouble filling those stem roles
in general uh for years some of it is
that women pursued it and then when they
realized it was so male dominated and
the
the uh unavoidable in some ways sexism
that comes with that
you know the easier road often is to
drop out when you're in college or to
change your career once you've started
getting into it i mean it
unfortunately that's a really common
story and the same thing happens with
minorities
where you know one of the people when we
interview in the film
you know when he worked with a team and
he would run a team and he would go to
uh clients offices and talk to them they
would always defer to the white
guy assuming that they were in charge
right yeah they never they expected
the that they weren't part of that team
and so
i think part of it is this changing our
expectations of what it is
one of the troubles i've always had with
software
you know i've been in it for about 30
years is when i talk to people and want
to encourage
people to get into this career because
it it
for some people can be like a generally
generationally changing
career like it can really change the the
trajectory of families and all of this
and what i hear from them
women people of color whatever the case
may be
is i couldn't do that because i was
never good at math and
i don't think that math is that required
for computer science like the computers
do most
most of the math for us and so i want to
sort of lower the bar of what we
think of as and promote as what computer
science is
right it's effectively problem solving
that happens to be solved with typing
right
you know we're not building rockets
we're not designing 3d engines
like 90 percent of all software that's
written
it doesn't require you know you don't
know how to do matrix math
or calculus yeah that's a really great
point there was actually a recent
nature paper that said that your ability
to learn a second natural language is
more predictable
predictive for your ability to learn a
programming language than math ability
and i think there's a lot to it that
it's not just
that we equate programming and math
skills it's also
what we believe about math skills is
typically that you have to be born
with it right you have to be born with
the magine whereas for natural language
it is way more that if you put some
effort in you can learn a bit of german
or spanish
so i think that's also something we know
for women um
that if they know that with a little bit
of effort they can get better then they
will put in the effort but if it's like
oh you have to be born for it then
women as you already pointed out just
think oh you know i'm not born for it so
why spend the effort because i'm not
going to get good at it anyway because i
don't have the
like the math gene yeah it's very
interesting to me this whole notion of
like
the math and the math gene and all that
because i think
we've we learned later in our life just
how
uh unimportant a lot of this ends up
being like that we
as people are good at a lot of different
things and maybe not everything
and that software has expanded when i
started like i would design all the uis
i'm comfortable sitting at a keyboard
and typing
and so that's what all the apps i wrote
looked like
but the users we used to sort of you
know shoehorn or
or um force the users into acting like
people that were comfortable with
computers it's only in the last maybe 15
years
that we really went oh you know what if
they were easier to use
we wouldn't have to train them as much
they would like
using the software they wouldn't be
afraid of it like all these things
uh that in in some ways these other
groups are
are better than you know than uh uh
you know technophiles just in the uh um
you know in their parents basement as
the stereotype goes right
it's we can make
better informed you know sort of
decisions about software
because we're seeing other perspectives
and we're and we're admitting that we're
not the best at everything which which i
think is
is part of this that you know keeping
people out was like well software has to
look like this because that's the only
way that we ever
use software you know this is of course
an argument that people make for more
diverse teams is that more diverse teams
also
have the ability to improve the product
because you get these different
perspectives
do you think that's also a an important
reason like you said there are social
justice reasons why you want to
bring people to programming it's a great
career so that's a reason but
there might also be this reason that
more diverse teams just seem to build
better things
absolutely yeah you know and it's not
just diversity in the
you know in the sense of oh we need to
bring this many women in and we need to
bring this
many people it's it's more to
intersectionality as as
scott hanselman likes to talk about and
that is like if you're building medical
software
do you have people on your team that
have medical problems are you building
uh software for the military do you have
anyone on your team that
has been in the military before like
that understands
and has the exposure that isn't the same
uh story you know one of the things that
happens here in the states not as much
uh i think where you're at but in the
states when you're developing
uh something often teams won't
especially web products they
won't necessarily test them against low
bandwidth
internet users because of course every
developer has what
one gigabit to their house and all that
oh this works fine on my machine in the
office and it
it's going to work fine when i'm home or
on my 5g phone
but if you're going after users that
don't have that
you know that don't have the affluence
that usually comes with being a software
developer
we i want us to open up our minds about
that a little bit and realize that we're
not
nearly all the same as we want to be
yeah that's a great point
i want to talk a little bit more about
the leaky pipeline like why are we
losing people so the one point is we
don't get people into computer science
programs we don't get them into boot
camps
but then another reason is they they
drop out minorities and you already
mentioned that
sometimes minorities drop out because
they aren't seen
as playing the part they don't look like
the manager or they don't look like the
team lead
but what do you think are some other
reasons that people drop out
of the field and and also what can we do
to stop that
well you know it was difficult for the
film
finding uh a lot of especially women to
talk about it on camera
because they you know they didn't want
to be many of them didn't want to be
labeled as difficult
or or you know hurt their career by
talking about the the fact that there is
real sexism in software there's no way
to get around it
and when you have people that
in the software industry even people of
color or women we kind of expect them to
act like white guys
and what i mean by that is it's very
male to sort of
talk about your ideas proselytize or
push them really hard
uh be the loud person that runs every
meeting like that alpha
personality is somewhat expected and
those softer voices in the room whether
they're women or even white guys that
don't have that
they tend to struggle more because we
have this expectation of
what of how we act and i think this is
what
lends that to it you know it it's part
of it that like oh i don't fit in here
or i'm not respected
but i don't want to ignore the fact that
there's also having to deal with just
the sexism of
of not being considered strong but also
you know straight up
overt uh sexism of
uh why are you here this is a boys club
you know
why do you wear skirts more why don't
you smile more like all that stuff that
we know happens in all industries like
i'm not saying that
software is worse than x y or z and i
think some people have
sort of come at me like why are you
saying bad things about the software
industry
i think it's wrong everywhere but this
is my industry and so that's why i care
about it here
right this is this is where i live yeah
i do think there are indeed two sides to
it
you have this general sexism of women
being
nothing as serious and also general
racism of non-white people being seen as
less of leaders and just not fitting the
part playing the role
but then also software has this other
image
of being very geeky i've been to
offices of software companies where you
know there are
mario walls and star wars and this
it all projects this idea of look this
is what you shoot like where i think if
you go to a law firm
i think you will be less likely to see
star trek posters on the wall or or
anything that really
projects so clearly what you're what you
shoot like what you should be interested
in
so i i think that specific part of
in programming are our hobbies
and our personalities being so tied to
your job it's also adding to
to the issues that we have our industry
seems to be built
to a certain extent on this on this geek
image and
and i'm really wondering about your
perspective of like
can this be changed should this be
changed
should all programmers like geeky stuff
i don't i don't know
what is your take on that you know i
don't think
i don't think it's a requirement i think
that that is part of the
uh you know we in the last 10 or 15
years
when i was more into hiring than i am
these days
uh i noticed that there was a lot of
push for do they fit in
and and that was sort of code for
do they look and act like we do are they
going to be interested in the same
things when we go to lunch with them are
they going to talk about the next
uh you know avengers movie and and
and that is i think that it continues to
be just a natural barrier
to you know being accepting of
different sorts of people that are going
to benefit your team and and being
comfortable with people that you know
don't look like you don't act like you
don't aren't attracted to the same sort
of people you are i mean like
it really comes down to this sort of
literalness and
if it were only over like there is over
racism and sexism
and we should get rid of it everywhere
but i think the real
problem we have in software isn't that
over it's the um
implicit bias the bias that we don't
think is really bias
you know when i go to a conference and i
see a woman
do i think she's a recruiter or do i
think she's a developer
now my first instinct is probably wrong
but i can make a decision to make it
different
and that you know that's one of the
things that i'm hoping to sort of
encourage is to people to just
reconsider what what
you know what they're thinking because i
don't think everyone needs to be that
way
i hid for many many years the dark
deep deep secret that i don't like comic
book and i don't like
star trek right like
and i you know i it's like i'm out of
central casting in hollywood
i look like i should love those things
anime
can't stand it like i should like all
that stuff
because you know i sort of fit the bill
but i don't i really don't
i don't like buffy you know there's i
could continue like
a bunch of stuff that like i don't
understand it
and that's fine and i would sort of like
go i
i wanted to fit in peer pressure and all
that and i would go oh yeah
but uh when i was less confident that's
sort of the thing
that i felt like i had to do to fit in
and
and that happens all over the place when
i moved to boston
i realized that when i met people
outside the eit department
that i didn't know how to talk to them
and so i started list
listening to sports radio so that i
could at least say oh did you hear about
sports team last night winning right
even though i didn't really care but it
was something that i could just
again fit in and i don't think that's
healthy in the long
run there are things that i love and i'm
passionate about and i'm geeky about and
they're
some things that i'm not and i think
that tends to
tends to push people out because they're
like what if i
like want to go home at the end of the
day without thinking about software
what if i don't really feel like the
only thing that i can talk to people
like after work when we go to grab a
drink is
you know what the new uh spa library is
like
please don't ever talk to me about what
the next tech
thing is when we're trying to relax tell
me about who you are and
the things you like to do and like
you're more interesting than that
i know that you don't have to pretend to
yeah i think that's actually also a big
part of the stereotype of programming
is that it should be your only hobby
or one of the things that are acceptable
like movies and comic books and stuff
like that
but all the other hobbies are are are
not accepted so
i think many people are like you
probably sort of pretended to like
some things that they didn't like and i
think the the reverse is also true if i
look at my own career like i really like
knitting which is a really
female hobby and when i was in grad
school i was like one of the few
uh grad students in software engineering
like i didn't do any knitting and i
didn't talk about anything at all and i
think a part of that was
because clearly that wasn't the hobby
that fits
what my job was and that fit what
everyone else was doing
so i sort of not did it and then of
course after a while
it's not sustainable like you're you're
you're not liking buffy it's just not
sustainable after a while you're just
like well i've grown up i will just tell
people what i like and what i don't like
but but it's it's actually really hard
and i want to talk a little bit more
about
how we can change that so maybe people
are now listening to the show
and they're like uh oh our office has
billiards tables and star trek posters
and free beers and
all the stuff that you know might
attract
um white males that might be less
interesting
to other people but how do you go about
changing that
and in feminist theory you have this
idea of a killjoy
which is a person that points out these
issues
and therefore isn't really liked right
if you're a female developer or you're a
black developer and you're like
you know why are you giving out free
beers i would be more interested in
you know free lunch or whatever some
something different or
i don't want to have star trek posters i
want to have a knitting workshop as a
team outing
how do you start that conversation how
do you
how do you do that while also retaining
your position of being in the in crowd
that's a
really difficult balance it's hugely
difficult because i
you know the the uh archetype of of the
killjoy
is real and a lot of people are like oh
i don't want to be that person
i don't you know i don't have uh you
know one
i don't have an answer i would love to
have an answer but i know for me
that what i've encouraged people that
i've mentored is to just be honest
you know i uh the there's a story i tell
i worked at a company and every day we
would all go out
down to downstairs and have lunch
together and
it was a time we talked about mostly
tech things but it was a good way for us
to sort of bond
with a you know a bunch of east asian
and american
guy developers like it it was sort of
what you
think of when you see the billiard balls
and all that and
i had started a a change in the way i
ate and so i started bringing my lunch
instead
of buying it downstairs and i just felt
weird about it and like
i'm gonna miss this thing and all of
this and you know what no one
even noticed that i wasn't eating food
bought at whatever restaurant everybody
bought i was so concerned
with what i thought they thought of me
that when i started
to just go you know what this is who i
am and in the first five or ten years of
most people's software career
they spend it in this being afraid of
getting
found out that this this need this peer
pressure to fit in
is so important and you know when i
started talking about things that i
actually cared about that i thought were
interesting that weren't
the things that everyone else was
talking about everyone
started to bring up the things that they
really liked you know
and it sort of opened that up you know
one of the other guys
like to fly airplanes and another guy
you know wanted to do this or that and i
think that
starts the opening of what is acceptable
and then we can go you know what
even though it looks like we're all the
same we're not
and if that's the case why are we
keeping people that we don't think
fit into this image that none of us
really
fulfill why are we keeping them out in
general so it's not about tearing down
the mario posters it's i think it's more
about
you know um our personal
ability to be honest with each other and
not worry
and not worry as much about you know
being ridiculed or
or not fitting in and this this this
mirrors the same problem i see with like
sexism in the workplace we did a a
fairly small
uh um survey but a survey nonetheless
where we wanted to ask
people about a bunch of things that
ended up sort of shaping the way the
movie went
one of them was have you ever witnessed
sexual
harassment or sexism in the workplace
like not that you'd personally done it
but did you witness it
and the numbers were astonishingly high
and that told me something that told me
that there are people and i've certainly
been
guilty of this in the past and and
hopefully i won't be guilty of in the
future
that see it happening and are afraid to
speak up
because i don't know whether we can
curse on here or not but frankly
being able to go bob you're foolish
leave her alone
or that what the hell are you bringing
in here
is that is the beginning of fighting
sexism not
not having an you know a human resources
meeting that
human resources meeting isn't going to
change it but when we hold each other
accountable i think
i think that's where it starts yeah and
i think that's definitely also true
i mean for for bob clearly harassing
someone
but also the smaller things
whereas you know sometimes a female team
member might propose an idea and then
she doesn't listen to you and then a
meal team member
sort of rephrases the same thing as as
sometimes women like to say in a lower
voice just the same idea
rephrased and then all of a sudden
people are listening and there's also
these
tiny ideas where someone in the meeting
could say
hey i think that that's what stephanie
just said right and then
bring the ball back to her that also
is sexism that bystanders can really
counter or help relieve that at least
it's nice to know that someone also
noticed this and that you can
change culture like this so it isn't
just about um overt harassment it's also
about
these tiny like motions of oh
her idea isn't so serious or she isn't
so devoted to the company or whatever
things that
aren't really true but are just
someone's views
and what what happens is even if you
even if you just view it through the
prism
of white male developers there's a
percentage of those developers who
aren't they aren't the kind of they
aren't extroverts
that want to be in the front of the
meeting and putting ideas out
and we're losing their perspective
because the only people were listening
to
male female black white uh east asian
whatever
are the people that are willing to just
be loud in the beginning of the meeting
and telling people to sit down and
listen to everybody or to get that
feedback
is part of that and that that to me
solves the problem that well hopefully
uh ameliorates the problem of let's get
all those voices heard
you know we we aren't just getting
diversity
so that we can say that in our head
count we have diversity
we want to have diversity of ideas not
just
people and part of that is like you know
the quietest voice in the room
is often the one that has the best idea
but if they
never can speak up because you know the
alpha
developer over there who wants everyone
to know how wonderful he is
never shuts up you know what i mean
i mean it's it's it's difficult and
you know unfortunately i've been that
guy before and
i was that guy when my
uh self-confidence was at its lowest
like that that's how i knew i
there's this notion i have that
arrogance and software development is
almost
always really about self-confidence lack
of self-confidence like
if i if i puff my chest up a bit no one
will know how weak i
am and and uh and that hurts
people who are trying to just be real
when all you
hear is just the you know the puffed up
chest over and over and over again
you know i i would love to be able to
take those people aside and say
we know you're good at what you do you
have to you don't have to
prove it to us anymore yeah so you know
what i mean
yeah yeah definitely and this actually
segues nicely into the topic i want to
talk about more
in the rest of the episode because so
far we talked about
the industry as a whole and now we're
moving a little bit towards
a team culture within a company so we're
already talking about issues
within a team a person and that might be
a straight white male is maybe more
likely to play the role of
the leader the ideas guy who always
dominates a meeting
suppose you have a team in which
non-white males also participate
what do we do like how do you change
that team dynamic how do you change
meetings what do we concretely do to
make
this culture within companies within
teams more inclusive
you know i think it's difficult i think
we're so focused on the team lead
idea instead of of us being
more of what a i think teams usually
really are which is
a group of people so one of the things i
i found out while making the film that
was
it's sort of meta in this way is that
when i started making the movie
i realized what i wasn't good at like
there's a bunch of stuff about making a
movie that
i'm not good at and so i had to go find
people that were that i could
team up with that were interested in
what i was doing and i realized that
this is exactly what should be happening
in software
like finding the people that are good at
what and passionate about
the things that they're good at putting
together a team of
all you know super loud alpha
developers we already know doesn't work
right
you need to have people across the
spectrum that are that care about
different things if even if you look at
it in
sort of the microcosm of a team having
someone that
understands and is good with the back
end versus the front end
or that understands the data stores
versus
you know the javascript or whatever the
case may be finding that team but
instead of just thinking about it as
skills but thinking about it as
the interactions you know when it when a
meeting starts
there shouldn't be a leader to a meeting
you should be all coming together and
trying to come up
with ideas together without someone
having to be
you know the leader you know in uh
i don't know how it works in football
admittedly because i don't
uh i tried watching it when i lived in
in
amsterdam for a while and i just don't
understand it but
in most sports teams there might be a
leader but their job isn't to tell
everyone how to do everything and that's
what happens in software
is like oh just just move over i know
what i'm doing
clearly you don't there's this whole i
there's this whole mentality of
uh i i'm the only one that can do it
right and i'm only doing
letting you do part of it because i
don't have the tune
time to write it all and i think we have
to get away from that
we're all good and bad at different
things in software outside of software
whatever the case may be
and embracing that instead of trying to
pretend
that you're great at everything you know
it's just i think it's i think it's
causing our teams to be toxic
yeah so that sounds like a great idea
you know having more
a flat team without a leader having
meetings without a leader
and maybe some of our listeners are like
yeah i would like that
but how do you have any like concrete
tips on how to get to that culture i
really already liked your idea of
sitting down and talking about
personalities and interests to
just get to know each other better but
then i guess
you're not immediately at the situation
where you are
leader free and everyone's voice is
equally heard
how to do that well i again i don't know
that i have a concrete
solution for it i will tell you that
what i did when i was leading teams
was my my role was mentor
not uh general like that's the way i
tried to view my job i wanted to make
everyone successful
and that often meant helping them when
they wanted
help and not helping them when i thought
they needed help like there's this
this idea of uh you know
letting them fail on their own place if
we if i think leaders sometimes
want to protect anyone from having any
sense of failure
that they swoop in and don't let them
fail and learn from those failures like
his failure to me
is just is how you learn i i
don't learn until i i don't learn that
the stove is hot until i put my hand on
there a couple of times
and i'll never learn if someone doesn't
let me do it
and and so i'm not suggesting that it
needs to be a completely flat
structure but that we think about the
team lead in a different way
in some organizations some organizations
that they just want to take their most
productive developers and make them the
leader
that doesn't always work you need
someone that really
you know wants to have the success and
has the
soft skills to allow them to do that
that
that aren't going to be oh my god this
guy works under me is really good
he's going to want my job great
because do you want this job forever
like it
it it's never made a lot of sense to me
um so
i wish i had a magic bullet i think at
the end of the day
that my goal is for people to be
thinking about that they don't need to
wear a mask at work
you spend so much time at work that i
want
to be true with these people and trust
them
as much as possible the only the places
where i was most successful
in my job is when i was at companies
that trusted me
so when i go to places they're like no i
don't have that admin access to my own
machine
and i can't make that decision and you
know whatever the case may be i'm like
they're just setting you up for failure
i if
if i don't trust you to do the work
that i want you to do why are you still
here
like if if i have lost faith in you you
should go find another job
it's kind of my mentality but if that's
not the case then i need to trust you
and um and that that comes with within a
team of just going
i'm just gonna put it out there this is
you know you know whether it's
as simple as i don't like buffy the
vampire or
it's as complex as you know what i don't
agree with our position
but everyone else thinks this is the
right way to go and i'm on board
and i'm not going to come back and tell
you you know i told you it was going to
be wrong if it fails
i was heard and that's all i can expect
you know what i mean
and by having that i think more people
are going to be willing to
to be open and share i just want i you
know
it may be pollyanna to think that we can
just not be
playing games when we go to work and try
to
you know create this careers that we go
on this
magic career path that we think we're
going to be on that is
never correct that you know that
invariably we
we diverge from and
by doing that i think we get these added
bonuses of like
of course we want people that don't look
like us and don't sound like us and
don't think of like us on the team
because that's how
that's how we can succeed more as a
group and as a company and as an
organization or whatever the
you know the organizational unit is
you're working in
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve
a game status intelligent predictive
systems
effortless automation and technology and
people working in harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a-game for more
information
so what do you think is key to creating
trust
what i think you just said was one thing
that is really important is
everyone should feel like they're hurt
like their voices are being heard or
that they are being taken seriously
and that seems to me definitely to be an
ingredient in creating
trust in a team and trusting your
company but
yeah you might not have all the answers
but what is your experience maybe you
can give an example of
a team in which there wasn't so much
trust and you or someone else did
something to
create more trust you know
one of the things that i learned early
on that i've tried to
you know i've tried to encourage people
is that trust is a two-way
street and what i mean by that is uh
you yes you want to be heard you want to
have your
opinions but when i trust you
with what i think is the wrong or right
thing to do it also means that if
if we don't agree on what we're going to
do
that you're not just going to abandon
ship
and so a lot of times what happens in
these cases is
yeah you were heard and as a team or as
a group
we've decided to go another way i
you sabotaging is not trusting like
accepting that the group dynamic is that
we're going to try to come to the right
thing and that will
pivot if we're wrong like the i've i've
one of the ideas that i know doesn't
work for everybody i wish it did
but that i've sort of modeled my life
around is
i'd rather make a wrong decision than
not make a decision
so i'd love to make a right decision but
i'd rather
make a decision and it be wrong than be
stuck
not making a decision to have one more
meeting let's discuss it one more time
and we'll everyone will finally agree on
what we're doing now that's not how
that's not how the world works sometimes
you just have to barrel ahead
get your knee scuffed and realize that
you have to change course
and there's value in that knee getting
scuffed
and i think the problem we have
sometimes with trust
is the our leaders the people
running the teams or more normally you
know the people above them
uh want the
trust from the developers of the teams
but don't want to give
it like oh i'm going to give you a date
on releasing this
or i'm going to give you what we're
planning to do in this period of time
you have to trust i'm going to get there
and not come in and micromanage and
you know bring up a gantt chart every
four days to see are we there are we
there we're there
and that's and that's tough because you
know i think a lot of people
are worried about the you know
trajectory of their career or keeping
their job or
whatever the case may be and that trust
is hard earned
but it's one of those things i you know
i think it's very similar to being in a
relationship
if you don't trust which has
risk associated with it if you are
willing to trust there's risk associated
to it
but the reward is also much higher you
can stay in a super safe place but
you're
if you're not going to take the risk of
of challenging yourself
by trusting your company or opening up
about what you like and don't like or
you know that you really don't want the
window
cube in your company or whatever the
case may be
sometimes it's gonna it's gonna feel bad
but ultimately i think that that risk is
rewarded over the long term on average
even though it's going to feel bad
sometimes if you're going to try to
protect yourself from ever feeling bad
we're going to get to what we've got
which is a bunch of people just afraid
to tell other people what they really
think
and and and what that does in the case
of
software is it keeps people out
that might be better at
doing the things that we want to do and
that have different experiences that
maybe we don't understand
and that's you know i think in that way
it's tragic
uh you know in the in the film i
ultimately
come to the conclusion that this
industry isn't as
bad as i feared but also isn't as
inclusive as i want
it's somewhere in the middle and that
the i think the only way to fix this
isn't to have you know a conference
where we all talk about it or that we
count the number of
of women and people of color who speak
at events i don't think that solves it i
think it
becomes personally responsible for us to
when we have that
thought in the back of our head of like
they must not know what they're doing
because they're a woman
or boy i wonder where they're from
they're probably not a very good
developer
that you acknowledge it and go i'm not
going to act on it
and i'm i'm going to ignore it and i'm
going to act my actions matter way more
than
than my thoughts yeah i think that's a
great point to make where
many people maybe all people have
certain
implicit biases like they need might
think if they're at a conference oh that
woman oh she's probably in sales
and it's it's not terrible if you think
that because you are
the product of society everyone is but
you don't have to act on it you can
think
hmm maybe that's a little bit biased
and also maybe i don't have to express
my expectation maybe i can just read her
name tag and see what
job she actually has so i think that's
the concrete point that people can do
that
you're not a terrible person for having
these biases you're not a terrible
person for thinking that way
but think before you act you don't have
to act upon it yeah
i mean as a as a somewhat famous person
just said you know
if you really think you're the least
racist person in the room
he might not be you know
i want to zoom in a little bit more on
more specific
situations in which team dynamics and
power dynamics play a role
for example many people within companies
of course do all sorts of feedback
sessions like
for a promotion maybe your peers will
have to give you feedback or if you're
doing a code review
in a team and you might be the let's say
the sole female developer or the soul
black developer and you're giving
feedback
to to an alpha male in the team how do
you go about
giving that type of feedback and you
know you might say oh you have to create
trust but
assume that some people in our audience
are in such a team
they don't immediately have the
possibility to create trust
what do you do in such a situation and
maybe also what can other
people in a team do to support them well
it's interesting that you mentioned code
reviews because
code reviews are sort of a the place
where i usually see when i'm brought
into sort of review teams and such that
you can tell
whether a team is toxic or not because
someone looking at my code uh is a
really risky thing for me emotionally
like it all the uh um imposter syndrome
stuff i have which i haven't really
gotten rid of
over the last 30 years it still crops up
when someone looks at my code you know
my my stomach tightens up and i'm
worried
so i try to go into those situations
going i'm going to learn something here
and i might learn that my code's fine i
might learn
that i don't agree with you about
something or i might learn that i can do
something better
and when you're the one giving the
feedback
trying to do it without the the notion
of shame or blame
like um that that's where i see
in in sort of code reviews inside
companies it sometimes becomes
like this deal of either no one is
giving
any of the real feedback because they're
afraid of hurting someone else's
feelings
or the reverse is where everyone's just
going in so that they can
notch their belt with another i told
them
and neither of those are healthy like
you might think that the notch belt is
the
worst part of it i actually think it's
the other where people are so afraid
of what someone's going to say about
their code that they don't
want to take that risk and when you're
a woman or a person of color when you're
a minority in the room
it becomes even more so you're afraid of
what you know
of not fitting in or not or you know
becoming the target of the developer who
likes to
count the number of spaces and find out
whether you put tabs
in your in your in your code like we all
know that person
and we need to sort of as a team
acknowledge what's going on with them
you know that confrontation i think is
worth it even though in the moment it
feels
awful on both sides like having to have
that
talk feels as bad as having that talk
being given to you
um there was a i was working with the
chriselles
um years ago and we were it was a
startup
and we were actually in an apartment we
weren't even in an office yet we were
just in an apartment
and there are two developers in each of
the bedrooms
and i walked in one day and uh and uh
chris said we need to talk i was like
okay and as we went
went to his office the guy that i shared
uh
the my room with was already in there
sitting and i thought oh this is gonna
be bad
this is gonna be really bad but them
telling me what they didn't like which
was
uh i i tend to curse and grunt when i'm
coding which i didn't realize at the
time
but it was really unnerving to my my
roommate
was good because i was like oh okay now
that i have the information i can do
something with it
but until someone you know sort of
confronts that moment it comes back to
that same thing of like
you know uh why don't you sit down for a
minute and
let's let sheila talk like you don't
need to
interrupt her anymore you know they're
they're these soft skills about
learning how to listen learning how to
speak to each ot other people
learning how not to be too aggressive or
too passive
that everyone needs to learn and so in
those moments of whether you're getting
a review or other things just being
honest with what you expect
me and my wife have a have sort of a
system that
that works for us we're both a little
touchy around our creative projects
and so when uh um when
i asked her to like proofread something
of mine i tell her pretty clearly what i
want out of it
like do i want you to tell me how
wonderful i am which sometimes i do
do i want you to tell me if there's
mistakes in it or do i want you to
really critique it like
and so by giving them what giving her
what the expectation is
and vice versa she does the same thing
with me
we know what this is expected because as
a developer
i want to find a problem and solve it
even if none exists and this happens a
lot
in these interactions oh you want me to
review my co-worker let me think of
everything that could be a problem
instead of going you know
that those three problems that i might
write down really don't matter
like in the in the big scheme of things
they're awesome and
you know i'm worried about that they
throw in missed pieces of paper into
their trash like
it doesn't really matter it doesn't
really affect me and so
you know some of that is just you know i
don't have a
the black and white answer but empathy
is good in our industry if we can find
it
and i actually think it's excellent
advice to clearly say what you expect in
a code review in episode 400 we
interviewed dr
dr michaela greiler about specifically
code
reviews and there she also said the same
actually i didn't think of it when i was
preparing the interview but she also
said
if you're going to do a code review you
have to say what do i want do i want to
know
generally the idea of the code is like
going in the right direction
do i want to get feedback on how clean
everything is how well organized because
at different stages
in development you might indeed be
looking for different types of feedback
so i think that's
concrete and good advice that doesn't
only apply to getting feedback from your
spouse but could also apply
in a code review and what's interesting
there
is there i think it comes to
developers too or it's important for
developers
to think about the difference between
is this good code or versus is this how
i would have done it
and that took me a long time to learn
like just because i wanted to approach
this way doesn't mean it's bad
and so i used to go into code reviews or
look over
team members code and go you know
i would have approached it this way and
so maybe i'm gonna get them to fix it
well it didn't need to be fixed do you
know what i mean
it's yeah it was fine it wasn't the way
i would have approached it but that
doesn't make it worse
or better and likely better right i only
have one perspective and me assuming
that everyone that works with me should
do it the same way
is just as pejoratively bad
yeah and these are also things of course
again forming trust and creating a team
that you can discuss
beforehand yeah so you suppose code is
written in a certain style
and you would like it in a different
style you can have a meeting and discuss
hey what style do we
prefer as a team otherwise you get this
back and forth like oh you should do it
this way no it should be that way
those are things also that can be
decided independently of code
yeah it's interesting when uh i had a
client recently who uh he was like
should we go ahead and create like a a
code style document for what we wanted
to look like and i went
that is the worst idea ever like you're
going to have a lot of meetings
and it's not going to change anything uh
the best
you know when i was brought up
when i was growing up and i was learning
to code i was learning on commodore 64s
and vic 20s
and didn't know what i was doing like i
was just a kid i wasn't like i went to
college before i started doing that
and so i got this a lot of really bad
habits
and people telling me i had a bad habit
never solved it
what solved it was i worked for somebody
who had code that was
so beautiful that i wanted to emulate it
and so that's another thing when i was
running teams that i really
i always hoped for was that i was
representing the example
instead of trying to enforce the rules
so then suppose you want to agree on a
certain style what you would say is
some team members would just create code
that they think is good and then new
members
fall into the code base and pick up the
habits naturally
yeah and i would think that you you i
have told them before is you know
there's already code here just follow
the same design
like don't i don't want to have the
conversation about four
versus two spaces i don't want to have
the decision uh the
the discussion about a space before the
the um parentheses like none of that is
making our code better
it's just uh it's just not and so if you
see code especially if you're editing
someone else's code follow the style
and it's interesting that open source
has really pushed that
on me like i get into a project i'm like
oh my god i'm like no no don't fix any
of that that none of that matters you're
here to
help do a pull request they've got the
style of
the way they have their code just follow
it there's no you're not going to make
yourself
better feel better by putting in a uh
pull request that is
all just chaining tabs and spaces and
formatting and you know especially these
days where the ide
can make it comfortable for you and then
reformat it back to them and
like i just don't think it matters as
long as it's it's
sane like one of the places where i
always talk to people about is like
object and and method and function names
are important
where the parentheses are it doesn't
like
sort of pick your battles and do you
think this is true for
for team leadership as well where it's
less important to have clear documents
of this is how we do projects
and it's more important to create a
culture and to
model the kind of behavior that you
would also expect from your teammates
i think that's the only way it's ever
worked for me you know
uh having the employee guy uh guidebook
as we used to have when i was earlier in
my career
was just something to to use as a weapon
against
against employees and again that goes
against this idea of trusting the people
that work with you
and so i also mean that when it comes
down to it
i can't take the shortcuts just because
i'm the team lead or i'm the
you know whatever the case may be uh as
a consultant i can't do
especially can't do it as a consultant
because if if they're going to use
code that i'm giving them as an exemplar
to something else they're doing
i can't just go well you're paying me by
the hour so i'm going to take these
shortcuts
it's if you can't represent the example
why are you leading these people
there's one more topic i want to talk
about in this this episode and that's
job interviews so in job interviews
there of course also inclusivity and
diversity plays your role
because some people might show up to a
job interview not looking like a
developer and also at the more content
level
um we have this culture of job
interviews that we talked about in
episode 412
where you know these whiteboard
algorithm interviews
that certain people might have more
exposure to if they go to a
computer science program for example
where they're really prepared for these
type of interviews
people with a different background might
not have access to the information
needed for
these job interviews how do you deal
with that you want to get people in but
also we talked about that before you
have this idea of culture fits
and sometimes i i have heard from women
that they're rejected from a job
interview
and then the interviewer says well we
don't think you'll be happy here
and then even the interview is like yeah
and you know i think they were right i
wouldn't be happy there but
isn't isn't that a problem if a
qualified person that fits the job
is rejected for probably not being happy
and then who has this
issue there might be lots of people in
our audience
that do job interviews what can they do
to to get the right people in
and then maybe also to retain them later
on but specifically how to how to get
them
in i think we have to think about
developers in a different way than we do
you know the whole sort a linked list
whiteboard thing is i i don't think is
useful
but also the you know how many hubcaps
are there in london
problem that is also a sort of interview
question that happens
because what it comes down to to me when
i uh when i have hired people
is i am not looking for people with a
specific skill
or a specific mindset i'm looking for
somebody
that can problem solve because to me
there's
really two main jobs that developers do
one is learn
and one is solve problems like those are
the two things
so whether you like i've been asked
some insane questions of like in this
c-sharp spec
what should you blah blah blah i went
yeah i don't know i would look it up
like i don't know and that's that's fine
interestingly i had taken an approach
with software interviews
uh because i knew the things i didn't
want and it wasn't again about skill
it was uh often about soft skills so one
of the things i would do in interviews
was try to get
the person i was interviewing to say i
don't know
because it feels so epidemic that people
are like i'm supposed to know everything
and part of what i need from you is to
go i don't know but let's find out
i don't know i i uh early in my career i
had an opportunity to go work with
some pretty big names and software and i
just felt overwhelmed by it and when we
started working together that was one of
the things
i would ask them about something that
like was in a book they wrote
and they went i don't know let's find
out i was like wait wait wait
you don't know and that's okay like it
took that for me to sort of get that
message out of like oh okay the guy
i say guy there i go using my uh
my sexism but the person that i want
working in my company
is not the person that's going to
pretend that they know everything
that's toxic that's scary because
don't bluff me just be again be honest
and
and that way i can trust you if you're
like
oh i don't know why that's happening
i'll find out for you
or let's dig in or let's you know dive
into the code and debug and see what's
going on
instead of this this this pretending and
you know one of the things that that
baffles me
in europe is that uh the european cvs
often will have the photograph of the
person they're interviewing
and in the states it's actually illegal
it's part of
our anti-discrimination laws which i'm
not sure are doing very good
but so the first time i saw a european
cv with a picture on it was like
what because there is this
in in the us there's this uh hiring bias
that happens
because they don't have a white enough
name or that their name is a woman's
name like
where it doesn't even get to the
interview and
uh that's tragic to me it's like really
are you really gonna go by
this because it they sound like they're
from the caribbean or because uh it's a
woman and you expect
the only person that can do database
design as a guide like
there's no great way to do that because
i don't always think that
a problem with them going
i think a man is better for this but
instead going
oh this sounds like somebody that you
know would do this or
what do you mean there's flowers on your
resume i want it to be taken seriously
well come on
it's their resume they can look any way
they want it it's sort of
my stance on it i think the hallway we
hire is broken
and i really like that idea of yours
where you say i i want people to say i
don't know in a job interview because
that tells me a lot
how do you then in that small space of
an interview that's maybe
maybe an hour how do you then there
create the culture because you people
might be really reluctant to say i don't
know because they're like oh
i'm failing the interview because i
don't know an answer do you explicitly
tell people
this is the question and if you don't
know just tell me you don't know that's
okay
or do you look for people who are
already comfortable
saying they don't know i think it's
great advice but i wouldn't know how to
act on it
being an interviewer yeah it's difficult
because some of it is about how you come
across and i think a lot of
a lot of people that do interviews think
of it as someone adversarial
and and i think that's part of the
problem one of the things that
uh i have talked to a lot of people
about
is when they're interviewing sort of
being on the other side
is don't go into an interview hoping you
get the job
hope you can get out of the interview
finding out if you want the job
and it's the same on the other side is
let's figure out whether this is
the the right person but we also want
them to succeed
we want to hire somebody and
worst case if they don't work out
there are remedies for that that aren't
terribly difficult to deal with
and so i think this idea that like the
interview is this
right of passage and this you know
having to
scale the the castle walls to get in
is part of the problem is it is
we we're hiring people that are good at
interviewing not
hiring people that are good at software
yeah i think that's very true and as i
said
episode 412 talks a little bit more
about job interviews also how to
run them but i think this angle of trust
and making people feel included
really really adds something where i
like your remark of saying
we also want them to be successful
because we want to hire someone it's not
an exam
where they fail if you want to find out
if it's a fit
especially in the where we're at we're
literally having a hard time finding you
know software developers
in the us i often talk about it as
negative unemployment right
there are more jobs that haven't been
filled than we have people to fill them
and so why are we being so worried and
adversarial about
hiring about doing interviews if like
we need the people you know what i mean
yeah and the same is true of course for
the leaky pipeline and not getting
enough people in
where everyone's like oh i'm looking for
developers but yeah you know we
we disencourage women and people of
color in many different ways and
and also we are struggling to find
people that just just
doesn't seem too smart one of the people
we talked about uh
talked to the chancellor of uc davis in
california
he was talking about if we could
encourage the black community in the
united states
to become software developers or bnit in
general
that in the united states before covid
we had about three
three and a half million unemployed and
a million unfilled i.t jobs
you know like what we're missing
something like we're missing an
important piece in the middle
we've got empty seats and people but we
don't have a good way to
to fill them because i think i think it
becomes this thing where we're like
we're so
worried about finding the right person
that we're missing the people that don't
interview well or
who are self-spoken or you know whatever
the case may be
or that they're in many cases i know i
said this before but i really want to
reiterate it that
we're not even letting them interview
like
uh you know oh it's a 22 year old woman
how is she gonna know how to do this
tech thing you know she's not even gonna
know how to wear khakis and
and uh uh grow you know
grow a neck beard how is she gonna fit
in yeah and also i think to a certain
extent that we also
miss out on people that have potential
and that could learn a lot because
teams might not be good at teaching so
much so they might not know how to deal
with someone
who clearly for example is very skilled
in a different programming language but
not in this programming language and
they're really like
but how will we teach them javascript if
they're coming for c
from c or something and that's not
necessarily about the candidate because
probably it's not
that hard to pick up a new programming
language but it's also about the team
not knowing how to effectively own more
people
i i also think culturally we need to uh
teach developers especially in colleges
that
well the language you're working on here
rarely is going to be the last language
you
you know developing you know in the
united states
there's a nasa is trying to hire fortran
developers because
they're all dead or retired like they
still have code
that's running on that and i don't think
that's happening much anymore i'm hoping
that
you know in 20 years i won't someone
won't go come find me because they still
are running silverlight right
but hopefully that isn't happening
anymore
i think that's a great way actually to
close the interview we've talked about
how big the problem is and you given
many solutions that people
that are interested in could apply to
make their teams more trustworthy and
more inclusive so that hopefully
we can be a more inclusive industry and
of course if people want to know more
they can watch your movie
where can we find your movie well that's
an interesting question
so you can view the trailer and visit
the movie website at helloworldfilm.com
hopefully pretty easy to spell there
hello worldfilm.com
and um you're able to pre-order it today
in north america uh we're working on
international
um distribution right now and i'm hoping
we'll have something to share
first of the year but we're planning on
coming to a a bunch of countries
some of them have different requirements
for us translating them
uh for example uh the netherlands
requires us to
have uh dutch subtitles and so we're
working on some of those things
okay so we just have to keep an eye on
the website then yeah
there's a newsletter you can sign up to
we don't we don't send many
emails but we every time we have an
announcement about a new
place that is released that's the best
way or follow me on twitter at
seanvoldemuth
because i i as most of my followers know
i'm i'm not sick of talking about it yet
okay we'll be sure to add links to the
show notes to the
film to the newsletter and to your
twitter account anything
else any other places we can find you on
the web uh pluralsight.com
i'm still writing and recording courses
for them i'm working on one on
uh view forms right now that i'm really
excited about so
uh that's always a good place to find me
i've given up all facebook uh properties
so you can't find me on instagram or
anything
great well thank you so much all for
being on the show today
thank you and this has been awesome
become an autonomous digital enterprise
and your business can achieve a game
status
intelligent predictive systems
effortless automation
and technology and people working in
harmony
this is the autonomous digital
enterprise
visit bmc.com a game for more
information
[Music]
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening